so we can do a few more exits from the
suitors they're covering wider range of
topics I was specifically selected him
so let's see how far we can get without
making it too long imagine because the
lake of water was disturbed stirred up
became muddy in that place a man with
eyes standing on the bank would not see
the oyster shells to gravel the pebbles
and the shoals of fish wandering around
and standing still for what reason
because of the disturbance of the water
in just this way because they're the big
way disturbed mine will know his own
welfare or dwell for another world or
both or he will realize the truly generally
or he will realize the truly generally
noble attainment a knowledge and vision
which is beyond human phenomena that is
impossible for what reason because
because of his disturbance of the mind
and we drink our 145 so the thing to
note here is that the disturbance of the
mind is something that the big was
responsible for or anyone everyone is
responsible for so the simile that the
muddy water it's not that something else
disturbed your mind because of which you
don't get to see the oyster shells the
gravel and so on it's you disturb your
mind on account of something else
because if the disturbance of the man
were truly rooted in outside of yourself
if it's not up to you well you wouldn't
be able to then overcome it because you
cannot possibly prevent water from from
being disturbing that sends these things
that are not in your control so sight
sound smell taste touch as they come
your way you cannot prevent that but you
can train the mind to not be disturbed
on account of it so well this well this
line pretty much says it's for an
untrained mind there will be disturbance
when met with disagreeable and then
because of the disturbance you will not
know what's good for you what's good for
the others what's good for both order
you would be able to truly realize the
genuine Noble
taemin knowledge and vision that's
beyond the human phenomenon that's
impossible so consequently 146 and
ethnic ayah says that the lake was
transparent clear and undisturbed that
place a man stand without standing on
the bank would see do as the shelter
Bravo and so on because of the non
disturbance of the water so his mind has
been trained there is no disturbance
amidst things that would disturb you and
that's why you will not lose the context
you will not lose the perspective on on
on what could feel on your own welfare
or what's beneficial for you what's
beneficial for others what's beneficial
for both then we have a good era of 148
it says because I do not see one other
thing that is quickly changing is the
mind so much so because it's not easy to
compare this quickly changing mind so
there's nothing there's no simile the
world will be given well quickly the
mind changes and now I'll give it a 151
and 152 because this mind this mind is
shining through luminous as some other
translations this mind is shining and it
is defiled by the superimposed
defilements the uninstructed ordinary
person does not know this as it is
therefore I say for the uninstructed
ordinary first from the original
development of mind so we have a whole
essay on this called
the infinity of the mind if I remember
correctly it's on our website to find it
there but in brief the point is that the
mind is in the aspect of your experience
as a whole the experience the whole is
the five aggregates there's nothing
outside of it whatever you can say
statement that there's nothing outside
of it is that which you can own an
account of your five aggregates so even
that's within so recognizing that the
mind is part of basically that
structure it's part of the five
aggregates means that they cannot truly
be affected by ignorance so the
defilements cannot defile the five
aggregates that's what it would amend in
other suitors where he said that Oba
Donna holding or attachment whatever you
want to translate it assumption we
translate this assumption is not the
five aggregates it's not in them it's
not part of them so it's not that you
like when you practice the Dhamma you
remove parts of the aggregates they were
corrupted and defiled and then you keep
the rest now all the aggregates are not
the defilements they cannot be in them
but as the Buddha said desire and lust
in regard to the five aggregates makes
oppa Donna be there pretty much in
regard to it kind of superimposed over
them so that's why it's meant ignorant
even the Buddha said of age' imminence
is beginningless means there was no
first point before which aggregates were
fine and then aggregates became ignorant
ignorant ignorance became part of the
aggregate so you can measure the first
point of origin there is no such point
because ignorance is not in the
aggregate it's pretty much your attitude
in regard to the five aggregates in
regard to experience the whole in regard
to the whole world and in realms and
devils and whatever else you might be
experiencing it's your attitude in
regard to it fueled by desire and lust
that ignorance is there that Oberon is
there that these superimpose defilements
are they're not recognizing where those
departments are not recognizing what the
problem is pretty much not recognizing
the defilements are not in the
aggregates you will then be dealing with the
you will then be dealing with the
aggregates looking after the aggregates
trying to get rid of the aggregates
thinking that's how you're dealing with
the defilements so that's what we the
means here the uninstructed ordinary
person doesn't understand this as it is
therefore there is no development of the
mind because what is the development of
the mind well it's freeing the mind from
the defilements so in order to free your
mind from defilements you need to know
where the defilements are so to speak
what they are
and if you don't know what they are you
will not be able to approve them so the
statement that this mind is luminous or
shining is basically a statement of of
that factual impossibility to be
polluted in itself but it doesn't mean
that you are free from pollution in
regard to your own mind and that's the
sole point here sometimes people
obviously mmm who haven't understood
what the fineman's are wouldn't jump to
conclusions say ah so the mind is always
pure that's implicitly saying I don't
need to do any work because the purity
is always there and it cannot be defiled
now the possibility for purity is always
there because there are certain things
that cannot be defiled such as mind such
as the fiber grades there doesn't mean
that your experience as a whole as in
your attitude toward your own mind
toward your own aggregates is free from
department so that's where the
defilements are and that's what they
need to be occluded from so then I'm
good 152 says because this this mind is
shining and it is liberated from those
superimposed defilements treacherous
defilement see the superimposed a
gratuitous because they cannot be there
uninstructed whirling not knowing that
they cannot be there that's why place
that's what he assumes them there that's
why refer that's what we translate the
Hupa Donna as assumption holding implies
you kind of holding on to something then
you see that you're holding it then you
choose to let it go but it's far more
softer than that Rupa Donna who put them
is assumption of being you assume
something to be to be that's it . you
assume something to be when that isn't
so and that's why you cannot like if you
become aware of who padam if you become
aware of your assumptions they cease to
be assumptions so they require a layer
of unawareness which is the layer of
ignorance as a necessary basis for it so
if you recognize the desire and lust are
completely treacherous they cannot
penetrate the sense objects cannot enter them
the sense objects cannot enter them
cannot consume them cannot but taking
them literally is this super imposed
assumption over your senses sense
objects and so on that because it's not
checked it's not restrained has resulted
in the views that are fueled by greed
aversion delusion desiring craving and
maintenance of that assumed state that's
women's sensuality is one of the
assumptions it's not really in the
things in the same sense defilements are
not in the mind or in the aggregates or
in the feeling or in the perception or
in the form it's in regard to them
because of your unchecked attitude and
desire and loss the words you haven't
understood it and that's why the one who
has understood that for him the Buddha
says there is the development of the
mind so it's basically if you haven't
understood this if you haven't developed
the right view there is no development
of the mind regardless of the amount of
effort he put in it and that's what
these short lines so succeed succinctly
say because this mind is shining it is
liberated from the superimpose
defilement the instructor nobody suppose
knows this as it is he understands how
that works he understands where the
problem is therefore I say for the
uninstructed novels have theories
development of the mind because he knows
it as it is he understood that
mm then on a slightly different note now
let's go to the one book of one in the
130 239 bhikkhus whatever big was
explained non demise Dhamma those
because are practicing for the harm of
many people for the unhappiness of many
for the non welfare for the harm for the
suffering of many there was in humans
and because those big was produce much
demerit and cause this good Dhamma to
disappear because whatever big was
explained Dhamma as non Dhamma those
because are practicing for the harm of
many for the unhappiness for non welfare
and so on
same goes for bhikkhu who explain non
vania's vinaya and vanaya is nonlinear
because we explain things not said
another by the target ah as having been
said another by the target ah and having
been selling out by the target as not
having been said and uttered by tatata
what has not been practiced by the
target as having been practiced by the
target and has been practiced by the
target as having not been practiced by
the target uh what has not been made
known by the target ah as having been
made known and what has been made known
as having not been made known and the
thing to note here is that see you like
you would read this passage and you
would kind of think oh yeah you know
some people might choose to do that but
this is this does not specify or rather
it's not a requirement that must be done
consciously so to speak in other words
in good faith you might be what you
might be thinking it's in good faith you
might be teaching the Dharma but because
you haven't understood it you haven't
understood what the Dhamma is you don't
have the right view yet you're teaching
it even if accidentally you are
misrepresenting it which you would be
without the right view you are it's
going to result in harm and
non welfare and so on so that's
important thing to keep in mind not like
if you like you know
express your view on what Dhamma is and
clearly state or this is power
understood it I'm not sure I don't know
for myself that's one thing but another
thing is to teach the Dhamma while you
know you don't know it but you assume
that simply by having a good intention
to help others it's fine it's and and
that's what that's the big problem here
it's not fine because when those people
here that is Dhamma they'll think that's
what Dhamma is and because of that they
will not look for what the actual damage
is so even your well-wishing intention
to teach the download to somebody not
being sure but it's the dumb your
teaching or just believing that it's a
dummy teaching but having verified it
for yourself there will be the sole
reason for blocking their progress and
then they're passed away and who knows
where they're going to be reborn and so
on and he was all and they had a chance
to to approach to them rightly but on
account of your well wishing misguided
instruction you let them astray pretty
much and same goes for anything else so
that's even in other suitors when you
read that you know like that sati sanam
the fisherman you know with a pernicious
wrong view that sensualities there's no
harm in it it's not like that there is
more on the radials who who just had
this view obstinately against the buddha
no they genuinely had that view could
not see anything wrong with it and they
thought it's good they thought they're
practicing the Dharma they thought
that's what the Buddha was teaching they
thought it's great and then they heard
that they would have said the opposite
then they kind of dispute it because
they could not understand it it's easy
to assume like they were this caricature
of people but they were most likely not
so you realize that whenever big was
explained on dumb as nama there's not a
bit it doesn't need to be done with this
evil intent behind no it simply states
if you explain non Dharma as Dhamma
that's why you're incurring harm full
stop doesn't matter why you do it if it
matters the Buddha would have said so in
this very suit